[SPEAKER_00]: You often describe going against the grain as not having things on your own terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: Will practicing rightly always be contrary to your preferences, or might there one day be a time that you actually prefer to go against the grain, when you know what that means?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I think initially, in the beginning, it's almost certainly going to be against your preferences.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, theoretically, it doesn't have to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: But my guess is that
[SPEAKER_01]: Those people would have already become arahants long time ago, while the dhamma was still a lot more alive.
[SPEAKER_01]: Today, what you have is people, they were, you know, they didn't make enough effort when the Buddha was around.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, having to, you know, just having to, like, even take on the precepts, if you look at it, you know, like, in terms of food, in terms of lying, in terms of entertainment, obviously, in terms of sexuality,
[SPEAKER_01]: That already goes quite heavily against a normal, decent person today.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you know, I don't mean like some really immoral, just a normal person, you know, white lies, this or that, it's not a big deal.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might not be a liar, you might not be a deceiver, but like entertainment, food, sensuality, it's like what's considered today normal, what's considered like a baseline for 99.9% of people, it will go against it, which means it's going to be unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: One way or the other.
[SPEAKER_01]: But exactly, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once you start practicing, if you start understanding things correctly, if the wisdom is actually being developed, and things are actually understood, not just, you know, intellectually accepted and so on, like, the motivation to practice, the goal for practice becomes obviously even more reinforced, more clear.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, even having to put up with kind of same
[SPEAKER_01]: Experiences of saying no to desire, to unwholesome tendencies and so on, it's not going to be even remotely unpleasant, because you know exactly what it leads to.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know exactly that the outcome of it will be far greater than if you just give in to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the more a person practices, the clearer things become, the easier the whole experience of that practice is.
[SPEAKER_01]: But... and that's why, again, it can't happen by an accident.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's only through your own effort of going against that grain, until you and your own mind start to prefer renunciation, start to prefer solitude over company, renunciation over desire, calmness over agitation.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Buddha was encouraging the monks to, like, develop delight in solitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: And tell them, like monks, practice renunciation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, develop pleasures of renunciation, so that you can... so that your mind will basically stop wanting pleasures of the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: Develop pains of renunciation, so that you will replace the pains of a household life or the household of the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, upgrade your pleasures and pain
[SPEAKER_01]: Instead of the central one, upgrading with the renunciation one.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then the point comes when, yeah, recognizing the mind of desire, saying no to it, will be actually felt pleasantly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, again, if I give you a poisonous drink, that you don't know it's poisonous, or you don't believe me that it's poisonous, and you're just so obsessed with the taste, addicted to the taste, because it's the most amazing taste you can imagine, you won't stop drinking it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, you actually learn that it's the poison.
[SPEAKER_01]: You start to notice the symptoms.
[SPEAKER_01]: You start to notice the difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you start to notice the difference in you when you don't drink it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you confirm it for yourself that there is a poison in the drink that I've been giving you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Would there be anything that I could say or do to make you drink it?
[SPEAKER_01]: When the danger has become apparent, it's like, oh, no, not a chance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, look, it's twice as nice as it was before.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: The actual threat to your life is seen directly
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if you engage with it, you are exposed to that danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's going to take a lot of effort to then undo that exposure, if you're lucky, if you have enough time to undo it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's how you recognize, and then it's like, you will gladly say no to the taste, to the sight, to the sound, smell, taste, touch, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you will be very joyful in doing so, because you're realizing, phew, I'm dodging a bullet here.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that relief is real.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then...